I came out of this experience of
studying consciousness and looking at
all the theories of consciousness. I
don't want to give it away but we have
no idea about consciousness really how
it's how how brain matter generates
consciousness if indeed that's how it
happens and there are people who doubt
that's how it happens it could be that
the brain channels consciousness right I
mean that if you conceive of
consciousness as like electromagnetic
waves
>> um brains are like radio receivers or TV
receivers you wouldn't you wouldn't look
in the TV set for the woman who gave you
the weather report you know she's not
there she's
So I don't know that that's true but
coming out of this experience of
studying this I don't dismiss an idea
like that you have to keep an open mind
because our presumption that you know
consciousness is an emergent property of
brain complexity that idea doesn't have
much traction. Welcome to the Hubberman
Lab podcast where we discuss science
[music] and science-based tools for
everyday life.
>> [music]
>> I'm Andrew Huberman and I'm a professor
of neurobiology and opthalmology at
Stanford School of Medicine. My guest
today is Michael Pollen, author of
landmark books including How to Change
Your Mind, which is about psychedelics,
The Botney of Desire, which is about how
humans and plants co-evolved and
collaborated to thrive. And The
Omnivore's Dilemma, which is an
incredible book about food and
nutrition, and most recently, the book A
World Appears: A Journey into
Consciousness. Michael Pollen is
considered by many, including me, to be
one of the most learned and thoughtful
people on topics that matter to all
humans and the things that we can do to
improve the human experience. Today, we
talk about many topics, but mostly we
focus on consciousness. And Michael
brings forward a new perspective that
integrates the best science on this
topic as well as philosophy and beyond.
And we get deep into this notion of the
ego, meaning our notion of self, and how
the ego is both important for and limits
our understanding of ourselves and life.
I should emphasize that the conversation
is not as abstract as I'm making it
sound. What I love about Michael Pollen
is he makes these topics very clear and
very concrete and in many cases
actionable. Thanks to Michael, by the
end of today's conversation, you will be
placed at the front edge of the
conversation and the data on this thing
that we call consciousness. You'll also
be versed on the latest of plant or what
is sometimes called psychedelic medicine
and perhaps most importantly what you
can do in your life to gain new
perspective on yourself, others, and the
planet at large. Before we begin, I'd
like to emphasize that this podcast is
separate from my teaching and research
roles at Stanford. It is however part of
my desire and effort to bring zero cost
to consumer information about science
and science related tools to the general
public. In keeping with that theme,
today's episode does include sponsors.
And now for my discussion with Michael
Pollen. Michael Pollen, welcome.
[clears throat]
>> Thank you. Good to be here.
>> Longtime fan of your books, of you. I've
had the privilege of speaking on stage
next to you, although mostly I was just
listening to you because you are this
amazing intersection of science writer.
You've written about food, psychedelics,
now consciousness. You'll tell us about
your new work on microbiome. I feel like
there's also some Wendel Berry woven in
there. Big Wendleberry.
>> Good. I didn't insult you. I didn't
shout about that.
>> We just lost him, too.
>> Oh, is that right?
>> He died like two weeks ago.
>> Oh my goodness. I know.
>> I'm a I'm like a huge Wendleberry fan.
>> Really? Me, too. Oh my goodness.
>> He taught me how to write and he taught
me how to think about certain things.
But I, you know, he had a huge influence
on I was very fond of him. Did
>> you ever meet him?
>> Oh, yeah. We had I interviewed him on
stage a few times. He interviewed me uh
in Lexington, Kentucky, and um about one
of my books. And I went to his house uh
and saw the long-legged house where he
writes on the river. He was always
trying to convince people like us about
the beauty of the tobacco culture.
and he kind of bracketed the cigarette
piece and the lung cancer piece, but the
culture was so beautiful and it was the
one time where the whole community got
together and racial lines were crossed
and the and the barns are gorgeous that
you know the the the tobacco barns with
the slots for drying. [snorts] So he he
wanted me to see those uh when I when I
came there.
>> Amazing. Yeah, I was feeling a little
anxious about bringing in that reference
in case you weren't a fan or you didn't
like his work, but clearly uh he was
calling in because um he was and for
those who don't know Wendel Barry is
this uh just magnificent poet who
>> and farmer and essaist. Yeah. And he um
you know actually when I was writing my
first book, Second Nature, I was trying
to figure out how to behave in the
garden. Um which is a microcosm of how
do we behave in nature, right? In other
words, I had pests. Uh, I had problems.
I had fertility issues. And the American
tradition of thinking about nature,
which goes back to Thorough and John
Mure and Emerson, is all about
celebrating the the wilderness and being
a spectator in nature. And of course,
the gardener can't afford to do that.
You have to act or you're not going to
have anything to eat. I had a headful of
thorough and Emerson from college and
graduate school and I was kind of
stymied about like what do I do about
weeds? You know there you telling me
weeds have just as much right to be in
your garden as the bean plant which is
crazy. But it was Wendell who who would
write these essays and he and he
convinced me, you know, he said we have
a legitimate quarrel with nature and
that our relationship is, you know, we
do have to make changes in nature to for
us to survive. And that's kind of who we
are is um the species who remakes nature
in various ways, but it has to be done
u sort of more like a marriage than a
domination. And uh so he just had a new
way of thinking about how to relate to
nature that really helped me and and
clarified my whole view of
environmentalism. So yeah, he's a great
hero.
>> Amazing. I'm saddened to hear that he
passed, but he certainly left behind.
>> Well, it's a pretty good run.
>> He had a very good run.
>> We will put some links to his work for
those that aren't familiar, and I
encourage anyone listening to just and
even those who are familiar with Wendell
to go read some of his poems. They're
they're they're an incredible journey
and uh
>> full stop.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah,
>> I'm with you.
>> Let's talk about consciousness.
>> As a neuroscientist, I was taught to
avoid this
>> issue. I hear it was the kiss of death
at a certain point, right?
>> Neuroscientists who had were already
very accomplished and famous in some
specific domain like memory or
neuromuscular junctions or whatever
could talk about it. They had permission
once they had their prizes and their um
stature. But some people have died on
the bed of nails that is the
consciousness discussion.
>> I almost did. [laughter]
>> Clearly not. But uh yeah, but maybe you
can tell us why why it's so so
precarious. But it's hard to define I
think is part of it. And uh kudos to you
for jumping in with uh both feet uh on
this one. So after having written a book
about consciousness essentially, do you
think that we can describe it in a
sentence? Can we give it an operational
definition or
>> it's such a strange phenomenon because
there is nothing we know with more
certainty than the fact that we're
conscious. It's the only thing we can be
sure of. Everything else we know through
consciousness, right? Everything else is
an inference, but we have this thing
that we know we have. But defining it is
difficult. So there are some very simple
definitions like subjective experience.
Um that's pretty good. Uh your toaster
doesn't have subjective experience. And
I would argue AIS don't have subjective
experience, but we can talk about that
later. Another popular, I don't know if
it's a definition exactly, is Thomas
Nagel, the uh the the philosopher in the
1970s wrote a brilliant essay called
what is it like to be a bat? And his
point was if it is like anything, then
you're conscious. So, even though we
don't know exactly what it's like to be
a bat, we can kind of imagine a creature
that navigates the world through sonar,
through sound waves instead of uh light,
photons. And so, okay, we can imagine
that. So, yes, bats are conscious by
that definition. Um, so is it like
something to be a computer is a real
question that I think we're going to
have to face. That's kind of what I use
as a definition. There's a lot of bells
and whistles that that human
consciousness has above that. We're not
just aware, but we're aware that we're
aware. We have self-reflection or
metacognition.
Emotion, you know, add that in. So, I
think humans have a very elaborated
kind of consciousness compared to some
other creatures. I make a distinction in
the book between sensience and
consciousness that some scientists make
and I find really useful. Sensience
being a more basic kind of ground floor
of consciousness that uh includes
awareness of your environment and a
recognition of changes whether they're
good or bad and that may be universal
and that may be a property of life. Um,
you can make a case that uh plants have
sensience, that single-sellled creatures
have sensience, and it may be something
you need to survive in an environment
that's constantly changing that you
can't program instinctually everything
you need to know. So that this would be
very useful. And consciousness is how we
do sensience. You know, we've added on
all these things. And every creature has
its own version of sensience based on
their body type, their sensorium, their
the scale of uh at which they live in in
time and space cuz it's kind of to to to
take our our our version of
consciousness and make that the standard
for everybody seems kind of crazy. This
thing about being able to respond to the
environment being some key component of
consciousness. Um, a plant can respond
to the environment. A barnacle
>> can respond to the environment.
>> Bacteria can.
>> Bacteria can. They can light sense. It's
they actually know the difference
between morning and evening.
>> And they have chemotaxis. They know
between the difference between something
that's good to eat and something that's
toxic.
>> Do you think they know they know? This
is the piece that I feel like the the
responding and the awareness that one is
responding is maybe where in my mind I
want to draw the line for some reason.
like a plant will you know you know
furlur and unfurl uh when in the
presence of light but does it know it's
responding and why I mean I suppose we
all the time respond to things and don't
know why but usually like I if I take a
sip of this tea and and it's too hot um
I have some sense of what I'm going to
do next and why I feel like the the
other stuff is just reflexive. Yeah,
it's reflexive, but it I I don't think
it's it's uh always programmed. I think
that there are novel situations that
even a plant confronts where they have
to have an intelligent response that
isn't necessarily um something
programmed in their genes. I mean, I I
took a deep dive into this field of
plant intelligence, which is
fascinating. I mean, the things we're
learning that plants can do that you
would not have guessed. I mean, you can
take a corn plant and [snorts]
uh it can navigate a maze. You can give
it a maze and and put some uh
fertilizer, some ammonium nitrate in one
like corner of it and the roots will
find the fastest uh path to that
ammonium nitrate. That's not a situation
it really experiences in nature. It has
to um that takes a certain kind of
intelligence, problem solving ability.
If you play the sound of caterpillars
chomping on leaves for a plant, they
will react to the sound uh and send uh